And welcome back to the lab.
연구실에 잘 돌아왔어요
Here we are in Jupyter Lab and we are going to go into week two.
주피터 연구소에 왔어요 이제 2주 차로 접어들죠
And we're going to go now to day two.
이제 둘째 날로 가보죠
Here we are radio day.
라디오 데이예요
Today we will build user interfaces using the outrageously simple Gradio framework.
오늘 우리는 사용자 인터페이스를 만들 겁니다 말도 안 되게 단순한 그래디오 프레임워크를 이용해서요
Prepare for joy.
기쁨을 준비하세요
There you go.
여기요
We will do some imports.
수입도 좀 할 거예요
And then this magical line import Gradio as GR.
그러디오가 GR를 상징하는 마법의 대사예요
And I said oh yeah.
그렇다고 대답했죠
So there we go.
자, 됐어요
And we load our environment variables in using the usual approach.
그리고 일반적인 접근법으로 환경 변수를 로드하죠
Um, and you'll recognize the next familiar cell, which is the three somewhat analogous commands to
다음으로 익숙한 셀은 API를 get up up 준비시키는
get our APIs up and ready.
다소 유사한 명령 3개죠
Okay.
네
So, uh, start by setting a system message in a variable, which is going to be the very generic UI,
변수에 시스템 메시지를 설정하는 것으로 시작합니다 아주 일반적인
a helpful assistant that is often the kind of standard starting point for a system message.
UI가 될 거예요 시스템 메시지의 표준 시작점인 보조죠
So that's what we will take.
그렇게 할 거예요
Um, and now we're going to wrap a call to GPT four mini.
이제 GPT 4 미니와의 통화를 마무리할 거예요
Uh, in a simple function like this, a message GPT takes a prompt messages equals.
이런 간단한 함수에서 GPT는 프롬프트 메시지의 등호를 취하죠
Now, by this point, uh, hopefully you were bored of this structure.
이쯤 되면 이 구조물에 질렸길 바라요
You know it so well, uh, a simple conversation structure, a list of dictionaries system, a system
잘 아시네요 간단한 대화 구조와 사전 시스템 목록 시스템 메시지 사용자,
message user, a user prompt, and then we call completion OpenAI chat, dot completions, dot create.
사용자 프롬프트 완성 오픈아이 채팅 .완성, .생성이죠
We pass in a model and we pass in the messages.
모형을 전달하고 메시지를 전달하죠
And what we return is the completion dot choices.
완료 .선택으로 반환되죠
We take the first choice dot message content.
선택 닷 메시지 콘텐츠를 선택해요
That is a function which we are wrapping to message GPT and return a response.
GPT 메시지를 래핑하고 응답을 반환하는 함수죠
Let's run that.
실행해 보죠
Let's just quickly try that out.
빨리 시험해 보죠
What should we say?
뭐라고 하죠?
Message GPT we've tried a few things that we know spell that right GPT we know what GPT is good at and
몇 가지를 시도해 보았습니다 GPT의 철자를 알고 있고 GPT의 장단점을 알고
what it's bad at.
있죠
Let's just try one more thing.
하나만 더 해 보죠
We know that it's not great at current events.
시사 문제에는 좋지 않죠
Let's just go with something very simple.
아주 단순한 걸로 가죠
What is today's date and let's see what GPT believes is today's date.
오늘 날짜는 언제죠? GPT는 오늘 날짜를 어떻게 인식하는지 보죠
Today's date is October the 3rd, 2023.
오늘은 2023년 10월 3일이에요
So a few things to note.
몇 가지 알아둘 게 있어요
One is that, as expected, it does not have a good sense of current events.
하나는 예상대로 시사 감각이 별로 없다는 거예요
And the second is that it does appear that its training data took it up until October 2023, just the
둘째, 훈련 데이터는 2023년 10월 초까지 지속된 것으로 보입니다.
beginning of October, uh, which is something that I alluded to before when it had said September.
9월이라고 했을 때 제가 암시했던 거죠.
I thought it was October, but I suppose if it's October the 3rd, then, then maybe it's a moot point.
10월인 줄 알았는데 10월 3일이면 논란의 여지가 있겠네요
It's a it's an end of September.
9월 말이 됐어요
Early October would be the answer anyways.
10월 초가 정답이겠죠
That is a very simple function that we've got there.
아주 간단한 함수예요
Put that to the back of your mind because we're going to come back to it later.
잠시 후 다루게 될 내용이니 마음 한구석에 두시고요.
It's time to create user interfaces.
사용자 인터페이스를 만들 때죠
First of all, nothing to do with data science.
우선 데이터 과학과는 아무 상관 없어요
Let's just see how to create a simple user interface.
간단한 사용자 인터페이스를 만드는 방법을 보죠
So here then is a very simple function called shout.
여기 샤우트라는 아주 간단한 함수가 있어요
And shout is going to take some text.
샤우트에는 텍스트가 좀 들어가요
And it's going to reply with that text in uppercase.
대문자로 답장할 거예요
That's a pretty simple one.
아주 간단한 질문이죠
So let's shout hello.
그럼 인사할까요?
And it says back hello and uppercase a shouty way.
Hello와 대문자 큰 소리로 대답하죠
Um, okay.
네
So I put it to you that building a sophisticated user interface with inputs and outputs that can convert
입력과 출력을 가지고 정교한 사용자 인터페이스를 구축하는 것은 작은 안녕을 큰 안녕으로 바꿀 수
a little hello to a big hello, is as simple as this.
있습니다. 이렇게 간단해요.
It's a two lines view is great interface.
두 줄짜리 뷰는 훌륭한 인터페이스죠
That means I want a new interface.
새 인터페이스가 필요하단 뜻이죠
You tell it the function that you want.
원하는 함수를 말해주세요
The function that is this user interface is built around, which in this case is shout.
사용자 인터페이스를 중심으로 한 함수인데 이 경우엔 샤우트죠
This function describes right here I'm passing in the function name and what you pass in.
이 함수는 제가 함수 이름을 넘기고 여러분이 넘기는 걸 설명해요
You then have to pass in inputs and outputs.
입력과 출력을 통과해야 하죠
And Gradio is very flexible about what you can pass in here.
그래디오는 융통성 있게 장면을 연출했어요
You can pass in lists of things if you've got multiple inputs and outputs.
입력과 출력이 여러 개라면 목록도 넘길 수 있어요
If you've only got one input and one output, you can just say what kind of thing it is as a string.
입력도 하나, 출력도 하나라면 문자열로서 그게 뭔지 그냥 말할 수 있어요
That's all it needs.
그거면 돼요
It will figure it all out.
다 해결될 거예요
Um, and just because this is two lines of code, but just to show you, we could just do it as one
이건 코드 두 줄이지만 여러분께 보여드리기 위해 코드 한 줄로
line of code because I'm really showing off here like that.
할 수도 있어요 이렇게 보여드리고 있으니까요
We can just put it all in one line, uh, and just run that and let's see what happens.
모든 걸 한 줄에 넣고 실행해 어떻게 되는지 보죠 Put it's go
We have ourselves here a little user interface.
사용자 인터페이스가 있어요
I'm going to type hello.
안녕하세요라고 칠게요
And I'm going to press submit.
제출을 누르죠
And there is a shouty hello right back at me.
그리고 저한테도 큰 소리로 인사를 하죠
It's a user interface with great controls around it.
훌륭한 컨트롤이 있는 사용자 인터페이스죠
And it's all been built running within this uh, this this this, uh, browser, just like that.
전부 이 브라우저 안에서 실행되도록 만들어졌어요
Now, one thing you might notice is that there's a flag button here, and a folder has been created
한 가지 눈치채셨을지 모르겠는데 여기 플래그 버튼이 있어요 플래그드라는 폴더가
over here called flagged.
여기 만들어졌죠
And this is a feature that comes out of the box with Gradio to allow functionality for users to flag
이건 Gradio와 함께 나오는 기능으로 사용자가 결과를 플래그 지정할 수
your results, which is a kind of common use case with machine learning, where you want users to be
있게 해줍니다 머신 러닝에서 흔히 사용되는 경우죠 사용자가 무슨
able to to see what's going on and make note if there's a problem with the results.
일이 벌어지는지 보고 결과에 문제가 있는지 기록하길 원하죠
But that out of the box functionality is not something we particularly want, and the way we can remove
하지만 그 기능성은 특별히 우리가 원하는 게 아니죠 그걸 제거하는
that is by passing in allow flagging equals never instead.
방법은 허용 플래깅 =never를 넘기는 거예요
So if I now run that instead, uh, again, I sort of resent the fact that I put that as two lines when
이제 실행해 볼게요. 두 줄로 놓은 것이 조금 억울하네요. 한 줄로 놓을 수도
I could equally well have done it as one line like that, just to really show you how simple it is.
있었는데 말이죠. 얼마나 간단한지 보여드리기 위해서요.
A single line.
한 줄이에요
Uh, and here we get, um, our user interface.
Get in UI 사용자 인터페이스예요
Uh, so there's a couple of things I've done about this that I want to mention.
이것과 관련해 제가 한 게 몇 가지 있어요
The first of them is with either of these cases, there's also a link that it gives you at the top here.
첫 번째는 이 두 케이스 중 어느 것이든 여기 위에 링크가 있어요
And if you click on this link, uh, it actually brings up your interface in an entirely separate window
이 링크를 클릭하면 완전히 분리된 창에서 인터페이스가 나타납니다
like this, which seems almost magical.
마법 같죠
Let's go.
가요
Hello.
안녕하세요
And it just works.
잘 어울려요
And that's because when you run Gradio, it actually runs a little web server running in the background.
그건 그레이디오를 실행할 때 백그라운드에서 실행되는 작은 웹 서버를 실행하기 때문이죠
Uh, running locally at a at whatever the first port it finds that's free.
처음 발견하는 포트에서 무료로 로컬에서 실행하는 거죠
After after some, some number, uh, after, I think 760 is where it begins and it starts going on
몇 번이 지나고 나서... 760번이었던 것 같아요 거기서부터 시작이죠
from there.
아마 마지막이 그거였을 거예요
Yeah.
네
Was it 760?
760개였나요?
Uh, so, um, it will run that little web server.
저 웹 서버를 실행할 거예요
And so you can either show that in the same Jupyter notebook in the output, or you can just bring it
그래서 같은 주피터 노트북에서 출력물에 보여줄 수도 있고 별도의
up in a separate screen in its own right, which is amazing.
화면에서 불러올 수도 있어요 그 자체로 훌륭하죠
But even more than that, the other thing I've shown here is that you can pass share equals true into
하지만 그보다 더 중요한 건 여기서 보여드린 다른 건 호출에서 공유 = true를 넘기는
your call.
거예요
And if you do that, then Gradio also serves the same interface on a public URL that you can share with
그렇게 하면 Gadio는 공용 URL 내의 동일한 인터페이스를 제공해 다른 사람들과 공유할
other people so that other people, colleagues that you're working with can use your same model and
수 있죠 여러분이 함께 일하는 다른 사람, 동료가 같은 모델을 사용해 여러분의
be able to come in and work on your prototype.
프로토타입을 작업할 수 있도록요
And this part is a little bit of the mind bending part of it.
이 부분은 좀 기가 막힌 비트예요
When someone brings up this user interface, which we'll do right now, it'll take just a second.
누가 사용자 인터페이스를 언급하면∙∙∙ 지금 할 건데 시간이 좀 걸려요
There's a bit more going on behind the scenes.
비트가 더 있어요
Here it comes.
나오네요
Here's the user interface.
이게 사용자 인터페이스예요
It looks it's of course the same as this.
당연히 이것과 똑같죠
I'll run hello.
내가 뛰어갈게 여보세요
And we'll see it working.
효과가 있을 거예요
What's happening here.
무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지요
This is of course being served by Gradio.
이건 물론 그래디오가 제공하죠
But when you call submit, when you press submit and call the function, that function hello is running
보내기를 호출할 때 보내기를 누르고 함수를 호출할 때 그 함수가 hello를
on, on my local box in this Jupyter environment right here.
실행합니다 여기 주피터 환경의 제 로컬 상자에서요
Uh, it's uh, it's a bit crazy.
비트가 좀 심하죠
It's still running the code as it's running on my box.
박스에서 실행되는 것처럼 여전히 코드를 실행하고 있어요
It's just there's a publicly available URL for it.
공개적으로 사용 가능한 URL 뿐이죠
It's kind of magic.
마법 같아요
Uh, let me explain what I mean by that.
무슨 뜻인지 설명해 드리죠
By going back here and printing here.
여기로 돌아가서 프린트하는 거죠
Shout has been called with input.
입력된 외침이 울렸어요
So now we are making very clear what's going on.
이제 상황을 분명히 설명하고 있어요
So when I run that it says shout has been called with input.
실행하면 Shout이 입력과 함께 호출되었다고 나오죠
Hello.
안녕하세요
So now let's come back here and run this again.
이제 여기로 돌아와서 다시 실행해보죠
So now it's running with this again a public URL.
이제 다시 공용 URL로 실행되고 있어요
Here it comes.
나오네요
I'm going to type.
타이핑 할게요
This is very cool.
정말 멋져요
And press submit.
제출을 누르세요
And obviously this is very cool as what comes back.
물론 이것도 아주 근사하죠
This is this is being hosted by Gradio.
이 쇼는 그래디오가 진행해요
But again the somewhat remarkable thing is if I come back here and look in my output, you'll see that
하지만 다시 한 번 주목할 만한 건 여기로 돌아와서 제 출력을 보면 입력과 함께 호출된
shout has been called with input.
호출이 보이시죠
This is very cool.
정말 멋져요
So the function that's running is running on my box.
실행되는 함수는 제 상자에서 실행되죠
The user interface is being served up through a public radio Gradio website, but the code is running
사용자 인터페이스는 공용 라디오 그래디오 웹사이트를 통해 제공되지만 코드는 제 로컬 박스에서 실행되고
on my local box, which is really amazing.
있어요, 정말 대단하죠
And what that means basically is that you can write models running on your local box, and you can build
그 말은 즉 로컬 박스에서 실행되는 모델을 작성할 수 있고 인터페이스를 빌드할
interfaces, and you can either bring them up locally for yourself, or you can share them with others.
수 있고 로컬에서 불러올 수도 있고 다른 사람과 공유할 수도 있다는 거죠
And as people work with those shared user interfaces, it's still calling the code that is running on
사람들이 공유 사용자 인터페이스를 작업하면서 여러분의 컴퓨터에서 실행 중인 코드를 여전히
your box incredibly useful.
호출하고 있어요 아주 유용하죠
And as you can imagine, for collaborating with people and sharing your models and getting your co-workers
상상이 되시겠지만 사람들과 협력하고 모델을 공유하고 동료들이
to to work with you, uh, it couldn't be easier.
함께 일하게 하는 건 정말 쉬운 일이에요
All right, so let's keep going and show a couple more things.
좋아요, 몇 가지 더 보여드리죠
I'm now going to bring up an interface which is going to specify inputs and outputs.
이제 인터페이스를 불러올게요 입력과 출력을 지정해주는 거죠
And you can see here what I'm doing is I'm saying that the the inputs it's a list.
여길 보시면 제가 하는 게∙∙∙ 입력이∙∙∙ 목록이죠
It's just got one thing in there.
한 가지만 들어 있어요
It's a text box.
텍스트 박스죠
It's got a label your message and it's got six lines.
메시지도 라벨에 6줄이나 돼요
The outputs is response and it's got eight lines.
반응이 출력력이고요 줄이 8개예요
Um, and it's calling the function shout.
함수 샤우트라고 부르네요
let's have a look at that and let's bring that up here.
그걸 보죠 여기로 불러오죠
And it comes up just as you'd expect and make it a bit bigger for you.
비트가 예상대로 나와서 좀 더 커지죠
There we go.
됐어요
There is a message.
메시지가 있어요
There's a response.
반응이 있어요
I can say hello yet again and I can press submit.
다시 Hello를 하고 제출을 누를 수 있어요
And over here comes the capitalized version.
여기 대문자 버전이 있어요
Very easy, nice and configurable.
아주 쉽고, 멋지고, 구성할 수 있죠
Looks like a good UI.
좋은 UI 같네요
Well, you can probably imagine what I'm going to suggest next.
이제 뭘 제안할지 짐작이 가실 거예요
Wouldn't it be great?
멋지지 않아요?
Wouldn't it be great if you could just replace that word shout with another function?
샤우트라는 단어를 다른 함수로 대체할 수 있다면 멋지지 않을까요?
Any function?
함수 같은 거요?
Why not a message GPT function that we wrote earlier?
왜 아까 만든 메시지 GPT 함수가 아닌 거죠?
You could just simply replace that word shout with that function, and you'd be able to have a user
그냥 Shout이라는 단어를 그 함수로 대체할 수 있어요 그럼 LLM 위에 빌드된
interface built on top of an LLM.
사용자 인터페이스가 생기죠
Wouldn't that just be great?
정말 멋지지 않아요?
Wouldn't it be great?
멋지지 않아요?
Ha ha.
네
Well, let's have a look.
한번 보죠
Here we go.
시작할게요
Same.
저도요
Same code.
코드가 같아요
We've replaced the function.
함수를 대체했어요
It's no longer shout.
소리 지르는 게 아니에요
It's now message GPT.
GPT에 메시지를 보내죠
Let's see what happens.
어떻게 되나 보죠
Let's bring that up in a separate window.
다른 창으로 보죠
Here it is.
여기 있네요
Please tell me a joke and we will submit that.
농담 하나 해 주시면 제출할게요
And we'll see what comes back.
결과를 기다려 보죠
Why did the Scarecrow win an award?
허수아비가 왜 상을 받았냐고요?
Because he was outstanding in his field.
자기 분야에서 뛰어난 사람이었으니까요
That's a great joke.
재미있는 농담이네요
Uh, okay.
네
A great joke from GPT four mini.
GPT 4 미니의 멋진 농담이네요
And a great example of how easy it is to make that bigger for you to build a user interface that is
사용자 인터페이스를 크게 만드는 게 얼마나 쉬운지 보여주는 좋은 예죠
running using an LLM behind the scenes.
LLM을 이용해 뒤에서 실행되는 거요
I hope that you are as overjoyed by this experience as I am.
당신도 나만큼 이 경험을 즐기길 바라요
I think Gradio is awesome.
그래디오는 대단해요
All right, I will see you next time when we're going to put Gradio to even more good use.
다음 시간에는 그래디오를 더 유용하게 사용할 겁니다 TREEN METING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETING TO DETY